John Kulig Collection of Boston Floating Hospital Memorabilia MS283
Tufts Archival Research Center
John Kulig Collection of Boston Floating Hospital Memorabilia
1894 -- 2022
Tufts Archival Research Center
Boston Floating Hospital
New England Medical Center
MS283
0.75 Linear Feet 1 oversized letter document box, 1 shared oversize box
This collection is comprised of memorabilia from the Boston Floating Hospital, compiled by Dr. John Kulig, former Director of Adolescent Medicine and pediatrician at the Floating Hospital for Children at Tufts Medical Center. Materials include realia, postcards, publications, annual reports, correspondence, receipts, photographs, a nurse's notebook, and a CD of a Pediatric Grand Rounds session, as well as historical research materials. The bulk of the collection dates from 1900 to 1927.
Scope and Contents
This collection is composed of memorabilia from the Boston Floating Hospital, collected by Dr. John Kulig, former Director of Adolescent Medicine and pediatrician at the Floating Hospital for Children at Tufts Medical Center. Materials include realia, postcards, publications, annual reports, correspondence, receipts, photographs, a nurse's notebook, and a CD of a Pediatric Grand Rounds session. Also included are research materials related to the history of the Floating Hospital, as well as to specific pieces of the collection. The materials range in date from 1894 to 2022, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1900 to 1927. The collection largely documents the early history of the Boston Floating Hospital, though later developments and its incorporation with the New England Medical Center are also represented.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series: Memorabilia; Photographs; Publications; and Archival documents and historical research.
Biographical / Historical
The Boston Floating Hospital (BFH) was founded by Rufus B. Tobey, a Congregational minister, in 1894. A ship that floated around Boston Harbor during the summer season, the BFH provided free medical care to indigent infants and children under the age of five. It was also known for studying children's diseases, innovations in milk formula, and for training nurses to instruct mothers in the care of sick children.
Two factors contributed to the establishment of the BFH, one charitable and one medical: the relatively widespread philanthropy work throughout New England, and the conviction by some that sea air was therapeutic during convalescence. Walking home from work on South Boston each evening, Reverend Tobey observed mothers bringing their children to the Boston waterfront, enabling them to breath the sea air. Learning of a hospital boat in New York, he, with the help of Edward Hale, spearheaded the effort to set up a similar institution in Boston. The BFH was a private charity and relied on donations for its endowment and expenses.
The barge Clifford, the BFH's first base of operations, made its maiden voyage in Boston Harbor on July 25, 1894. Attendance was around eighteen hundred, which nearly doubled by its second year. Medical students constituted most of the staff, under the supervision of chief physician J. B. Thornton. These first years brought significant accomplishments: a pharmacy, kindergarten, and "Modified Milk Department" were set up on board the Clifford, and by 1897, an inpatient department allowed for overnight stay, under the medical leadership of Samuel Breck. The BFH was officially incorporated by the state of Massachusetts in October of 1901. The Clifford was replaced by the Boston Floating Hospital Ship in 1906. The BFH also had an onshore department, located first in the North End before moving to Roxbury in 1916.
An early innovation for the BFH came by way of Francis Parkman Denny in the milk lab, who organized a human milk collection system for sick babies, a practice that eliminated the need for wet nurses. Further research in the milk lab contributed to the development of the first synthetic milk product, commonly known as Similac. Later on, the BFH established a bacteriological laboratory (1910), and a Post Graduate Training School for Nurses (1916).
On July 1, 1927, the Boston Floating Hospital Ship burnt. While the BFH was never again resurrected as a ship, it was rebuilt as a land-based facility because of its achievements in lowering the infant mortality rate. In 1930, it joined the Boston Dispensary (BD) and the Tufts College School of Medicine to form the New England Medical Center (NEMC). The land based BFH was located at 20 Ash Street in Boston, known as the Jackson Memorial Building, and officially opened on October 12, 1931. It continued to provide free outpatient services to the Boston community until November 1938, when it began charging for its services; a day's stay at the BFH cost five dollars. The NEMC consortium was beneficial to its three partners; students from Tufts College School of Medicine gained practical experiences at the BFH and BD, for example, and provided medical services in return. Laboratory tests and operations at NEMC throughout the years led to significant advances in medical treatment. According to a 1938 logbook, patients who suffered from upper respiratory infections were given throat cultures at NEMC, which motivated doctors to make this part of routine laboratory practice, in addition to blood and urine tests.
Up until 1965, NEMC existed as an overseer to its constituent organizations. In 1965, the Board of Trustees of the BFH voted yes to an official merger to integrate with the BD and the Pratt Clinic/New England Center Hospital (PC/NECH). (The Pratt Diagnostic Clinic, an extension of the Boston Dispensary, was established in 1938. It became a unit of NEMC in 1946 and was renamed New England Center Hospital.) The consolidation of these three organizations formed one corporation under the name the New England Medical Center Hospitals, Inc. In addition, during the merger, the Tufts-New England Medical Center (T-NEMC) had also been established as a separate corporation. T-NEMC had its own board, composed of members of the Board of Trustees of Tufts, as well as members of the Board of Governors of NEMC. The BFH opened a new facility in October of 1979, which was further expanded in 1982.
From 1930 to 2022, the Floating Hospital for Children was part of the Tufts Medical Center and is located in the Chinatown neighborhood of Boston. In 2020, the facility was renamed Tufts Children's Hospital, and in early 2022 it was announced that the Tufts Children's hospital inpatient pediatric ward would be shut down. The pediatric inpatient beds were to be converted into an adult intensive care unit, though the hospital planned to continue offering other pediatric services through clinics, outpatient procedures, and a neonatal intensive care unit.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. John Kulig is a pediatrician and the former Director of Adolescent Medicine at the Floating Hospital for Children at Tufts Medical Center. He is also a Professor Emeritus of Pediatrics at the Tufts University School of Medicine. Dr. Kulig graduated from the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine in Cincinnati, Ohio in 1975. Kulig has assisted in the information gathering for, and the publication of, multiple works on the history of the Boston Floating Hospital.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. John Kulig, 2022, accession number MS-2023-046.
Boston Floating Hospital; New England Medical Center; Medical history
- Memorabilia, circa 1900 -- 1950; MS283.000001; 0.2 Linear Feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains artifacts and memorabilia related to the Boston Floating Hospital. Types of materials include a model of the hospital ship, a commemorative tray, postcards, hospital stationary, and a commemorative calendar. These materials date from approximately 1900 to 1950.
  - Model of the hospital ship, circa 1900 -- 1930; MS283.000002 (Box 1, Object 1)
    Open for research.
  - Commemorative tray, circa 1900 -- 1920; MS283.000003 (Box 1, Object 2)
  - Boston Floating Hospital postcards, circa 1900 -- 1930; MS283.000004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    This file contains 21 postcards with various depictions of the Boston Floating Hospital ship.
  - Envelope addressed to Dr. William A. Hinton from the Boston Floating Hospital, 1921; MS283.000005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The First National Bank of Boston calendar, 1950; MS283.000006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    A monthly calendar for March 1950, produced by The First National Bank of Boston. The item includes an artistic image of the Boston Floating Hospital.
- Photographs, circa 1900 -- 2022; MS283.000007; 0.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains photographs of the Boston Floating Hospital and some of its faculty members. Materials date from approximately 1900 to 2022.
  - The Boston Floating Hospital, circa 1900 -- 1927; MS283.000008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Side view of the Boston Floating Hospital, circa 1900 -- 1927; MS283.000009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Doctors at the Boston Floating Hospital, 1912; MS283.000010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Faculty farewell harbor cruise, 2022; MS283.000011 (Shared 150, Folder 9)
  - The Boston Floating Hospital, circa 1900 -- 1927; MS283.000012 (Shared 150, Folder 10)
- Publications, 1894 -- 2008; MS283.000013; 0.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains publications related to the history and administration of the Boston Floating Hospital. Record types include annual reports, historical summaries, brochures, pamphlets, event programs, publications, and articles. The materials date from 1894 to 2008.
  - Annual reports, 1902, 1906; MS283.000014 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual reports, 1909, 1913; MS283.000015 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual reports, 1914, 1916; MS283.000016 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual report newsletters, 1977 -- 1978; MS283.000017 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual report, 1993; MS283.000018 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Historical sketch of the Boston Floating Hospital, 1903; MS283.000019 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - New England Magazine article on the Boston Floating Hospital, circa 1905 -- 1915; MS283.000020 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Floating Hospital for Infants and Children Physicians' Referral Guide, 1986; MS283.000021 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Event programs, 1894, 1989 -- 1994; MS283.000022 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    This file contains programs for the 1984 Benefit to the Boston Floating Hospital; the 1989 Floating Regatta; and the 1994 Floating Hospital for Children's Centennial Dinner.
  - Hygeia article on antiseptic used at the Boston Floating Hospital, 1932; MS283.000023 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pamphlet on the founding of the Boston Dispensary, circa 1996; MS283.000024 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Quest newsletter, 1991; MS283.000025 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Youth's Companion New England Edition, 1906; MS283.000026 (Shared 150, Folder 23)
  - Pediatric Grand Rounds CD, 2008; MS283.000027 (Box Shared Digital Media 1)
    This CD contains a Pediatric Grand Rounds session by Dr. John Kulig on the history of the Floating Hospital.
- Archival documents and historical research, circa 1902 -- 2020; MS283.000028; 0.1 Linear Feet
  This series contains original archival documents, as well as photocopies and historical research related to the history of the Boston Floating Hospital. Record types include notebooks, correspondence, receipts, and photocopies. The materials date from approximately 1902 to 2020.
  - Nurse's notebook, circa 1910; MS283.000029 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    This folder contains notes taken by C. Frances Battey during her time working as a nurse at the Boston Floating Hospital.
  - Postcard from C. Frances Battey to Mrs. B. H. Ingersoll, 1910; MS283.000030 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Historical research related to nurse's notebook and postcard, 2004; MS283.000031 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Tufts College Medical-Dental Schools tuition statement, 1924; MS283.000032 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence from Miss Isabel Chipman to Dr. C. W. Gaylord, 1909; MS283.000033 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    This folder contains a letter from Miss Isabel Chipman, Supt. of Nurses at the Boston Floating Hospital, to Dr. C. W. Gaylord requesting a reference for Miss Lewella Frances Benton.
  - Receipts for donations to the Boston Floating Hospital, 1902 -- 1903; MS283.000034 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Historical research on the Boston Floating Hospital, circa 2020; MS283.000035 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    This folder contains photocopies of historical documents and research notes related to the history of the Boston Floating Hospital.
  - Historical research on the Boston Floating Hospital, circa 1992 -- 2020; MS283.000036 (Box 1, Folder 31)